<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<page title="Editor/IDE plugins">
  <headsection>
    <downloadWarnings />
    <p>
      Below you can find syntax highlight definitions and other plugins for text editors and
      IDE-s that help you working with FreeMarker.
      We encourage everybody to develop and send syntax highlight definitions or other
      plugins for his/her favorite editor or IDE.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you know of another product that should appear
      here, <a href="mailto:freemarker-devel@lists.sourceforge.net">drop us a
      note</a>.
    </p>
  </headsection>
  <sections>
    <section title="Plugins">
      <p>Anybody who wants to improve these syntax highlights is welcome!</p>

      <h3>Eclipse</h3>
      <p>Features: Syntax highlighting, syntax error indicator, code completion for macro names and bean property names.</p>

      <h4>Installation</h4>
      <ol>
        <li>In Eclipse, "Help" / "Eclipse Marketplace…", search for "JBoss Tools", "Install". A tree of checkboxes will appear, uncheck all (by unchecking the root) except "FreeMarker IDE". (On old Eclipse you may have to use the <a href="http://www.jboss.org/tools/download/">JBoss Tools download page</a> instead.)</li>
        <li>If the plugin comes with a different FreeMarker version than the one your app works with, it will mark the usage of too fresh language features as errors, or the other way around. To fix this:<br /> Find <code>freemarker*.jar</code> under <code><i>&lt;yourHome></i>/.eclipse/</code>. Exit Eclipse, and overwrite it with the jar you want (the file name must remain the same, with the now false version number in it).<br />Note that downgrading or changes in the 1st or 2nd version number can (in theory) break the plugin.</li>
      </ol>

      <h3>Emacs</h3>
      <p>Features: Syntax highlighting, indentation, block folding, some code navigation. Emacs major-mode for editing Web templates, includes FreeMarker support among others.</p>
      <p><a href="http://web-mode.org/">The homepage of web-mode.el</a></p>

      <h3>NetBeans 6.0 or later</h3>
      <p>Features: Syntax highlighting, code completion, template navigation.</p>
      <p><a href="http://plugins.netbeans.org/PluginPortal/faces/PluginDetailPage.jsp?pluginid=3755">NetBeans plugin download page</a></p>

      <h3>TextPad 4 or later</h3>
      <p>Features: Syntax highlighting</p>
      <p>Last updated: 2003-03-24</p>
      <p><a href="download/editor/textpadftl.zip">Download textpadftl.zip</a></p>

      <h3>Vim ("Vi IMproved")</h3>
      <p>Features: Syntax highlighting</p>
      <p>Last updated: 2011-10-07</p>
      <p><a href="download/editor/ftl.vim">ftl.vim</a></p>

      <table class="shaded-table">

        <tr>
          <td>Eclipse (tried with 3.x)</td>
          <td>FreeMarker documentation in the Eclipse help system.<br />
              Requires FreeMarker 2.3rc1 (or later), or 2.2.6 (or later) from the 2.2.x series</td>
          <td>2004-03-13</td>
          <td><a href="download/editor/fm-eclipse-help.tar.gz">fm-eclipse-help.tar.gz</a></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Emacs (tried with 20.7)</td>
          <td>Syntax highlight</td>
          <td>0.1</td>
          <td><a href="download/editor/ftl.el">ftl.el</a></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Kate and KWrite (tried with Kate 2.5.10 and 3.2)</td>
          <td>Syntax highlight</td>
          <td>2009-08-08</td>
          <td><a href="download/editor/kwriteftl.tar.gz">kwriteftl.tar.gz</a></td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section title="Products that support FreeMarker out-of-the-box">
      <h3><a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea/" rel="nofollow">IntelliJ IDEA</a></h3>
      <p>A well-known feature-rich commercial Java IDE.</p>

      <h3><a href="http://www.jedit.org" rel="nofollow">jEdit</a></h3>
      <p>jEdit is a Free programmer’s text editor written in Java. It is highly customizable, extensible, and has an easy-to-use interface.</p>

      <h3><a href="http://www.modelworks.com" rel="nofollow">SitePad Pro</a></h3>
      <p>SitePad Pro is an Integrated Development Environment (IDE) for Java, HTML, VRML and other files. It’s commercial software.</p>
    </section>
  </sections>
</page>